Joseph A. Sposato Papers 1984.0032
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Joseph A. Sposato Papers
undated, 1934-1972
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0032
1.25 Linear Feet
Joseph Sposato was born 25 March 1912 in Retsof, NY. He began his employment at the American Velvet Company in 1927. He was a founding member of the first organized union at the company (1936) and was president of Local #110, Textile Workers Union of America (Stonington, CT) from 1940 until 1948 and elected again in 1952 until 1958. He retired from the American Velvet Company in 1980.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
Mr. Sposato donated his papers to the Connecticut Labor Archives on 18 April 1984.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative Files (1947-1972) is composed of documents regarding union committee work, union events and Sposato's work as public welfare director in Westerly, RI. Types of material include correspondence, minutes and printed materials. The series is arranged by subject.
Series II: Speeches and Seminars (1952-1969) contains typed and handwritten speeches given by Sposato to union groups and other organizations. Also included are reports, notes, and agendas from seminars Sposato participated in or attended.
Series III: Photographs and Memorabilia (undated, 1934-1972) contains positive print photographs of various convention activities (primarily Textile Workers Union of America) and photos of Sposato with other union officials. Memorabilia collected by Sposato includes the 1934 charter of union local #2 of the Velvet Workers Association.
Series IV: Printed Materials (1950-1971) is composed of union, professional and government publications. Also included are photocopied clippings from local Rhode Island newspapers regarding Sposato, company or union activities.
CHRONOLOGY
Joseph Sposato
1912 Retsof, New York
1913 Westerly, RI
1927 American Velvet Company
1936 Helped found the first organized union at the company
1937-1938 Velvet and Plush Workers of America
1940-1948 Textile Workers Union of America, Stonington, CT
1943 Appointed to War Price and Rationing Board War Manpower Commission, New London County, CT
1947 Westerly, RI
1952 Reelected president, Local #110
1959 Panel speaker at the 12th Annual Conference of Profit Sharing Council of America, Chicago, IL
1960 Northwestern University San Francisco, CA William Clarke, financial editor of the Chicago Tribune
1968 Stepped down as president, Local #110
1969 New York, NY
1975-1980 President, Southern New England Joint Board
1980 American Velvet Company
Scope and Content
The Joseph Sposato Papers document the labor and union activities of the donor. The collection includes correspondence, minutes, printed materials, notes, reports, agendas, memorabilia, photographs, and photocopied newspaper clippings.
Public welfare; Textile workers; Velvet industry; Notebooks; Speeches (documents); Correspondence; Notes; Rhode Island (state); Charities; Administrative records; Photographs; Photocopies; Publications (documents); Financial Records; Textile industry; Connecticut (state); Labor unions; Textile Workers Union of America. Local 110 (Stonington, Conn.); American Velvet Company
- Series I: Administrative Files, 1947-1972
  - Committee work
    - Planning board, 1952, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Profit sharing, 1955, 1960-1961, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Shop committee, 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Discipline Program, Morris Deutsch, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Public welfare, Westerly, RI, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Textile Workers Union of America
    - 17th biennial convention, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Events and conferences, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Speeches and Seminars, 1952-1969
  - Advances management research seminar, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - Incentive seminar, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Management seminar, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Speeches, 1952-1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: Photographs and Memorabilia, undated, 1934-1972
  - Photographs
    - Conventions
      - Profit and sharing, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - TWUA
        - 10th Biennial, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - 11th Biennial, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
        - 17th Biennial, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Sposato, Joseph, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Memorabilia
    - Certificate, TWUA, Local #110, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Charter - Velvet Workers, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Medal - Clothing and Textile Workers Union conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Membership card - TWUA, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series IV: Printed Material, 1950-1971
  - Connecticut Labor Department Monthly Bulletin, 1965 April - May (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - COPE—legislative activity manual, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The Federationist, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Helping to Write Your Nation's Laws," COPE, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Professional publications, 1953, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Run a Good Union Meeting," TWUA, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Union publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1952-1971 (Box 2, Folder 34)